גוט אפ. Gut off. Today's דף daf is קג, Kuf Gimmel, 103.
We pick up on קב עמוד ב. Kuf Beis Amud Beis. Of
course I obviously should mention that it's also September 11, the 15th
anniversary of the tragedy at the Twin Towers, so obviously our learning
should be in memory of all of those who died there and
those who gave their lives to save those who were trapped in
the Twin Towers. We pick up with the second wide line on
קב עמוד ב Kuf Beis Amud Beis and we're in the middle
of a discussion here about a משנה mishna that spoke that if
somebody was actually given money to buy wheat and bought barley, barley
and bought wheat, etc., whether or not what the consequence of that
would be. And the גמרא Gemara started to try to tie it
into the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir about whether שינוי shinui is קונה koneh or not קונה. koneh.
Of course it's a strange type of a comparison because it's one
thing if a person is given an object to make a, you
know, to make a like wood to make a chair out of
it, wool to dye it, where there's an object to be קונה
koneh as the raw material. Exactly here, what are you being קונה?
koneh? The idea of שינוי קונה shinui koneh is strange, but it
seems to be some type of a parallel that if you say
שינוי קונה shinui koneh according to רבי, Rabbi, who was it who
said שינוי קונה shinui koneh there? רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, then that would mean in a similar way if you're
not following the instructions of the what you were told to do
when you were given this money, then you're operating outside of your
שליחות shlichus and then somehow it's sort of like you're taking the
money and taking possession of the thing you're buying and you're not
sort of operating, you know, within the context of your שליחות, shlichus,
whereas if you say שינוי shinui is not קונה koneh when it's
a similar case by a craftsman or a tradesman, then here you
would be operating within your שליחות shlichus and you still would be
operating for the owner of the money, except because you're going against
the instructions, if there was any loss that came as a result
of it, you would have to be the one that suffered the
loss. So that was sort of the parallel that the גמרא Gemara
was setting up, and then the גמרא Gemara said, you know here,
even according to the one that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that normally
says, excuse me, I get this right wrong. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is שינוי קונה. shinui koneh. Right. But that here things would be
different because here, what do you call it? Here, you know it's
not that the person really just wants to make money, he really
doesn't care what the money's invested in. So the fact that you're
prepared to call this a שינוי shinui and stepping outside of the
שליחות, shlichus, right, it's not necessarily the same parameters because, you know,
if you're investing the money in something that winds up being a
successful investment, then you could really be considered the, you know, to
be operating within the context of the שליחות. shlichus. Okay, so those
were some of the issues that were discussed yesterday. Apparently what came
up also in yesterday's discussion was the issue of what do you
call it? היתר עסקה Heter Iska because, excuse me, היתר עסקה, Heter
Iska, I assume that the reason for that was because since the
גמרא Gemara described there a possibility of a way in which if
you operate outside of the שליחות, shlichus, then the הלכה halacha the
גמרא Gemara says is that any profit you make is equally divided.
If I gave you money to invest and that we'd be partners,
and then you stepped outside of the parameters of the sort of
instructions that I gave you, if you're within the instructions that I
gave you, any profit is shared and any loss is shared. But
if you step outside of those instructions, then any profit is shared
but any loss is your loss because, so that was sort of
the structure the גמרא Gemara set up, well for me. So it'd
be good for me for you to step outside the instructions and
I can only gain and not lose as a result. And again,
that's the idea that if we say that either שינוי shinui is
not קונה, koneh, the going against my instructions doesn't mean you take
possession of the money, again it's a funny analogy, or if we
say even if it normally is but because in the end I
really just care about making a profit, so then when you're making
profit you're always operating within the context, but if you're going against
it, then it's your fault that there's a loss. So given that
structure, that I could only gain and not lose, תוספות Tosfos basically
indicates that this is a nice sort of, he doesn't say it
in so many words, but a nice sort of way in which
in creating almost a work around for the idea of lending money
at interest. Because then what I could basically do, and this is
the way a היתר עסקה Heter Iska works is, you see when
the תורה Torah when you're not allowed to lend money in interest,
it's basically the, I mean the reason is is because we're dealing
with an agricultural society. So people didn't really borrow money for investment.
The תורה Torah imagines that the only reason people are borrowing money
is because they're poor. If the only reason people are borrowing money
is because they're poor, obviously it's improper, it's like taking advantage of
somebody to charge interest, or even if it's a reasonable thing to
do if the rates are reasonable, nevertheless you can understand why the
תורה Torah mandates not to do it, because it's actually essentially a
form of צדקה. tzedakah. But in a time when people borrow money
for commercial, for investment and commercial reasons and so on, then. obviously
it doesn't make as much sense. And interestingly, the גמרא Gemara then
creates a workaround called היתר עיסקא, Heter Iska, and, you know, sometimes
you feel a workaround is sort of cheating the system, but here
interestingly the workaround exactly reflects the reality that if it's about business
then, you know, then there's a sort of different set of values
that are as that are op- because we אין דורשין טעמא דקרא.
ein dorshin ta'ama dikra. You have to still work within, the תורה
Torah didn't limit it to those realities. But anyway, but you create
this workaround and the nature of the workaround is essentially the following.
If, let's say, I want to lend Michael here a thousand dollars
and pay 5% interest, but I'm not allowed to do that. So
what I basically do is I say to Michael something along the
lines of the following. I say Michael we're really I'm not going
to lend you a thousand dollars what we're really going to do
is we're really going to go into business and I'm going to
invest a thousand dollars in your business. And I'm really entitled to
all of the losses, all of the gains, all the losses, but
we'll make a deal, but I'll make you a deal, you pay
me a simple 5% fee as a, you know, as a sort
of and for that 5% that you're paying me, I'll sort of
keep my nose out of your books and, you know, whatever and
I'll trust you in terms of all the losses and, you know,
the gains or whatever da-da-da-da-da. So essentially then, you know, now how
exactly it works that he doesn't have to if he comes back
and says, you know, I invested the money and it's all gone,
how come he still has to pay me back? There's ways of
working about- around that as well, but essentially it's sort of the
interest becomes redefined as a fee and what our- what we're doing
is sort of redefined as a business rather than as a loan.
So anyway, תוספות Tosafot describes a similar type of a scenario because
if you can create a reality where all the loss is Michael's
but the gain is mine, so then I say Michael I'm investing
a thousand dollars in your business, here are the rules, and I
give him rules that are impossible to follow. The way תוספות Tosafot
basically says is, you know, only lend out this money if he's
in the business of lending money or whatever to I guess non-Jews
or whatever it might be, only lend this money if you can
get gold collateral, vessels and collateral, and only, you know, protect this
money like in the biggest like, you know, safe possible etc. something
that he'll never be able to do. And therefore, he's always operating
outside of my rules and therefore, any loss is- he has to
suffer, which means he'll always have to fully reimburse me for the
principal, but any gain I get half, so you can sort of
reframe the gain as- you know, the- the interest becomes a type
of a gain and so on. Anyway, those are some of the
interesting implications about what we learned yesterday. Now we have to get
onto today's דף. Daf. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught. This is two lines down
in the wide lines. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: הלוקח שדה בשם חבירו
אין כופין אותו למכור. Halokeach sadeh beshem chaveiro ein kofin oto limkor.
If somebody buys a field in the name of his friend, you
don't force him to sell it. ואם אמר לו על מנת, Ve'im
amar lo al menat, but if he says on the condition, כופין
אותו למכור, kofin oto limkor, you force him to sell it. Now
none of that seems to make any sense. So what's- what's going
on? מאי קאמר, Mai ka'amar, what's this being said here? אמר רב
ששת הכי קאמר, Amar Rav Sheshet hachi ka'amar, here's what's being said.
הלוקח שדה מחבירו בשם ריש גלותא. Halokeach sadeh mechaveiro beshem Reish Galuta.
I don't know where the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta came in here,
okay, but we're trying to make some sense out of this. So
you purchase a field from your friend. Now, in order to get
it so that people don't challenge the purchase, you know, once I
bu- I buy this field here from Michael, people are going to
come, now Michael's a tough guy, nobody's going to challenge him about
who owns the field, but once I have it, people are going
to say, "Oh, you know, it was really my field that Michael
had and you bought my field," and they're going to try to
take it away from me. There's going to be all of these
court cases I'm going to have- might have to deal with, you
know, or just any time anybody owns land they want to protect
themselves about nuisance suits. So the way I protect myself against a
nuisance suit is I basically write on the document and I basically
say I'm actually buying this for the sake of the ריש גלותא.
Reish Galuta. Okay, I'm buying this for the sake of, you know,
of the government. I'm not lying, it's sort of like a, you
know, it's a sort- like, yes, I'm lying, but it's a- but
it's a fiction. Okay, like I'm not- I'm certainly not tr- I'm
not tricking you, okay, but yes, apparently, I mean we'll see whether
that was like a standard thing that was done. Of course, if
it became too standard, then you aren't going to scare anybody off.
Okay, but then if people saw that it might be being purchased
for the government or, you know, then well not community but anyway,
nobody's going to challenge it. Okay, so אין כופין אותו. ein kofin
oto. Now, okay, הלוקח שדה מחבירו בשם ריש גלותא אין כופין אותו
ריש גלותא למכור. halokeach sadeh mechaveiro beshem Reish Galuta ein kofin oto
Reish Galuta limkor. So then you don't force the ריש גלותא Reish
Galuta like to say, "Hey, you know, Dov just bought this field,
it has your name on it, but we all know that Dov
was just doing it in order to protect his investment, so you
should go ahead and transfer the property to Dov." No, the ריש
גלותא Reish Galuta will say, "Thank you very much for that field
there, I'm not going to give it back to Dov, he bought
it for me, thank you very much." ואם אמר על מנת, Ve'im
amar al menat, but if I basi- but if when I buy
it, I basically buy it from Michael and I say, "Michael, I'm
only going to buy it from you in the name of the
ריש גלותא Reish Galuta on the condition that after I do this,
the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta goes ahead and re-sells it to me
and- and re-gives it to me," so then כופין אותו למכור, kofin
oto limkor, then you force the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta to sell
it to me. Of course, the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta could still
say no, and then my purchase from Michael would be בטל. butel.
But okay, now. אמר מר, amar mar, so that's actually one way
of reading it. We haven't even analyzed it. That's just the way
of reading it, working in some words. אמר מר, amar mar, so
let's analyze that. הלוקח שדה בשם ריש גלותא, halokeach sade besheim Reish
Galuta, אין כופין אותו ein kofin oso ריש גלותא Reish Galuta למכור,
limkor, מכלל דמקנה קניא ליה. michlal demikna kanya lei. So that sounds
like before we get the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta to sell it
to me, that the basic point is if I bought it on
his behalf, automatically the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta owns it. So לימא
פליגי דבני מערבא, leima peligi d'Bnei Maarava, let's say this argues with
בני מערבא, Bnei Maarava, דאמרי וכי מי הודיע לבעל חטין שהקנה חטין
לבעל הפיס? d'amri v'ki mi hodia l'baal chittin shehikna chittin l'baal apayas?
So this came up yesterday and I don't want to get into
exactly the context in which it came in yesterday, but the basic
point was was that if I'm going ahead and buying something and
I don't tell the person I'm buying it on behalf of somebody
else, but I don't tell the seller that I'm buying it on
behalf of that person, what happened when I was given the money
to invest and then I didn't actually tell the person for whom
I was buying it and so on, so one of the challenges
that was raised was if I am operating according to the agency
that I was given and I am purchasing something, do I have
to inform the seller for whom I am buying it for or
even without informing it it's understood that the guy who's selling it
to me for whether I'm acting on my behalf or whoever's behalf
I'm acting, he doesn't have to know who he's selling it to?
Okay, so the בני מערבא Bnei Maarava basically indicated that if you
don't inform him, then the seller, then you're not actually purchasing for
the person for whom you're buying. So this challenges it because it
sounds like the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta purchases it. Now I don't
really understand the גמרא's Gemara question because it sounded like I was
explicit to Michael that I was buying it for the ריש גלותא.
Reish Galuta. So I don't understand why that's a challenge to what
בני מערבא Bnei Maarava said. אי משום הא, im mishum ha, the
גמרא Gemara says, but that's essentially what the גמרא Gemara responds, but
I don't even understand the הוה אמינא. hava amina. אי משום הא
לא קשיא כגון דאודיע לבעל השדה. im mishum ha lo kashya k'gon
d'odia l'baal hasadeh. I told Michael I'm buying it for the ריש
גלותא. Reish Galuta. I mean, of course, if I didn't, then why
is it being written on the שטר shtar regardless? So it's a
very funny הוה אמינא, hava amina, what else the גמרא Gemara was
thinking. ואודעינהו לסהדי, va-odia-inu l'sahadi, and I told the witnesses. Okay, maybe
the גמרא Gemara imagined that I only told it to the witnesses
so they would write the document that way so the document would
help protect me against frivolous lawsuits, but I hadn't told Michael. So
now the answer is no, you told Michael. So anyway, that's why
we're bringing it in because of the tie-in to this statement of
the בני מערבא. Bnei Maarava. אלא אימא סיפא, ela eima seifa, but
okay fine, so that's the beginning of it. You don't force the...
That's a big implication, like let's say you want to buy a
house for your, you know, kid, you have to tell the lender?
The seller. Well, fine, yeah, the seller, but you know, whoever, like
you know, or the bank, right? Like they're essentially... No, you don't
have to tell the
person you're borrowing money from, you have to tell the person whom
you're selling it to, whom you're purchasing it for.
Right, that's the question, exactly.
אלא אימא סיפא, ela eima seifa, the גמרא Gemara says fine, forget
that part, let's look at the end.
על מנת, al manas, if I buy from Michael on the condition
that the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta transfers it to me, then you
force the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta to transfer it to me. על
מנת כופין את ריש גלותא למכור. al manas kofin es Reish Galuta
limkor. אמאי? amai? ולימא ריש גלותא לא יקרך בינא ולא זולך בינא.
v'leima Reish Galuta lo yikrachu b'ina v'lo zulach b'ina. Why do you
force the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta to do anything? The ריש גלותא
Reish Galuta could say 'I don't need your honor that you're writing
the שטר shtar in my name and I don't need your, you
know, your disparaging of my honor that you're getting me involved in
your tiny little, in your little transaction, and now you want me
to write a שטר shtar for you? Like what is this nonsense?'
אלא אמר אביי הכי קאמר, ela amar Abaye hachi ka-amar, fine, and
anyway it's pretty bizarre to introduce the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta into
that whole discussion. Anyway, so אביי Abaye says here's how to read
it. הלוקח שדה בשם חבירו, halokeach sade besheim chaveiro, we're going to
take out the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta phrase here although רב אשי
Rav Ashi maintains it. Anyway, I buy, אין כופין את המוכר למכור
זימנא אחריתי. ein kofin es hamocher limkor zimna achriti. So basically wait
a minute, let me just double check what this case is. Yeah
yeah yeah okay fine. So basically I mean רש"י Rashi does have
the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta story. The point is like this: Forget
the ריש גלותא. Reish Galuta. We're not going to
get the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta to
try to write the field
to me. I basically say to Michael essentially I want to buy
I want
to buy this field
for myself but I'd
like a שטר shtar in the name of the ריש גלותא Reish
Galuta so if any
nuisances come up I can always say 'Hey go fight the ריש
גלותא Reish Galuta it's his field.' But I really I want the
real document to be in my name, okay? I want two documents,
here you go, one to show you know one to show you
know one to show people who bother me and one that really
proves that I own it. Okay? So הלוקח שדה בשם חבירו, halokeach
sade besheim chaveiro, some have the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta some don't.
But anyway, it's in somebody else's name but that other person is
not the one who really owns it. So the field is in
my wife's name but it's really mine, okay? We don't have to
bring the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta into it. For whatever reason I
don't want the property in my name, maybe I want to keep
away creditors or whatever I want to keep away. I want to
put for tax purposes I want it in somebody else's name but
I want the other document that's the real document that I own
it. אין כופין את המוכר למכור זימנא אחריתי. ein kofin es hamocher
limkor zimna achriti. You don't force Michael here to write me another
document of sale to put it in my name. ואם אמר לו
על מנת, v'im amar lo al manas, but if I said to
Michael 'Michael I'm only buying it on the condition that after you
write the field that it belongs to either the ריש גלותא Reish
Galuta or my wife or whoever you write it to you also
write me a document that it belongs to me.' In that case
כופין את המוכר למכור. kofin es hamocher limkor. You force him. Okay
so now let's see if if that works. אמר מר, amar mar,
הלוקח שדה בשם חבירו אין כופין את המוכר למכור זימנא אחריתי. halokeach
sade besheim chaveiro ein kofin es hamocher limkor zimna achriti. פשיטא, peshita,
obviously. Michael says 'Look, if you want me to write that I
sold it to the ריש גלותא, Reish Galuta, I'll sell it to
the...' I'll write, or your wife, I'll write that, but how, why,
you know, why, how can you force me to write down another
document that I sold it to you? So גמרא Gemara says, isn't
that obvious? No, מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might have thought מצי
אמר ליה, matzi amar lei, I could say to Michael, listen buddy,
מידע ידעת דאנא לנפשאי שקילנא, midea yadat d'ana l'nafshei shekilna, you knew
that I was really purchasing it for myself, ופנחייא בעלמא הוא דקבעינא,
u-panchaya b'alma hu d'kaba'ina, and I really just wanted some way of
strengthening the sale, and that's why I was writing this other document,
right, in order so that, again, to somehow as a way of
avoiding nuisance suits. Okay, רש"י Rashi says פנחייא panchaya is some type
of חוזק, chozek, some type of protection. Okay. You knew that the
first document that you wrote in the name of ריש גלותא Reish
Galusa or whoever you wrote it in was not the real person
who owned that field. You know that was only a way of
getting rid, right, maybe a way of getting rid of nuisance suits.
You knew I was the real purchaser דקבעינא, d'kaba'ina, וזוזי בכדי לא
שדינא, v'zuzai b'hich-di lo shadina, I'm not throwing my money, flushing my
money down a toilet. Why would I be buying a field for
the ריש גלותא? Reish Galusa? I'm not an agent of the ריש
גלותא, Reish Galusa, you knew it wasn't serious, you knew it was
really just a way of, you know, giving me some type of
a protection. So אלא דעתא דכתב לי שטר אחרינא, ella da'ata d'kasav
li shtar achrina, I only bought it on the purpose, on the
condition, on the assumption that you would write me a document in
my name. So קא משמע לן, kamashma lan, so we're taught the
decision is that Michael can say back to me דאמר ליה, d'amar
lei, עניינא עבדי לך בהדי דזבנת ליה בשמיה סב יכתוב לך שטר
אחרינא. inyana avdi lach bahadi d'zavantalai b'shmei sav yichtav lach shtar achrina.
Listen buddy, so it's not my business to be concerned about your
business. Maybe you made some condition with the person that you were
buying it in their name. So I knew it was your money
or whatever, and I knew you said you wanted me to write
it in the name here of Joe, because everybody's afraid to take
on Joe. It doesn't sound like it's ריש גלותא Reish Galusa to
say Joe, you know, but everybody's afraid to take on Joe, okay,
so but I didn't know why, maybe you had some deal going
on with him, okay, it's not my business to know your business.
עניינא עבדי לך בהדי דזבנת ליה בשמיה, Inyana avdi lach bahadi d'zavantalai
b'shmei, maybe you had some condition or some deal going on with
the person in whose name you bought it. ויכתוב לך V'yichtav lach
Joe שטר אחרינא, shtar achrina, and Joe is going to write you
the document to show it to you. I don't have to know
your business, you buy it in the name of Joe, I'm writing
it, I'm writing you a שטר shtar in the name of Joe,
and do I have to care that you won't waste your money?
Who knows, maybe that's something to do with your arrangement with Joe.
אם אמר לאו אמנת, Im amar la'o a'menas, but if I say,
no, you're writing it only on the condition you also write me
a document in my name, כופין את המוכר למכור, kofin es hamocher
limkor, then you can force him to sell it. פשיטא, Pshita, obviously,
that was the condition of the sale and it's not like I
gotta get ריש גלותא Reish Galusa or I gotta get Joe to
write me a document, it's a condition that Michael writes me the
document. No, וצריכא, v'tzricha, you need it for the following case, דאמר
להו לסהדי קמי דידיה, d'amar lehu l'sahadei kamo d'didei, that I said
to witnesses in the presence of Michael, חזו דשטר אחרינא קבעינא מיניה.
chazu d'shtar achrina kaba'ina minai. I never said to Michael, 'Michael, I'm
only selling it to you on the condition that you write me
another document.' I said to the witnesses, 'Listen, I'm buying this in
the name of Joe here, but be aware,' and Michael is in
this room when I'm saying this, 'be aware,' I said to the
witnesses, 'that I'm going to be asking Michael for another document in
my name.' Okay, so presumably the חידוש chiddush is that that counts
as a stipulating with Michael. If I explicitly stipulated with Michael, obviously,
whatever the stipulation was, but I didn't explicitly, I just informed the
witnesses in his presence. Okay, so מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might
have thought מצי אמר ליה, matzi amar lei, that Michael could say
to me, אמינא שטר מהאי דקא שקלת בשמיה קאמרת. amina shtar mehach
d'ka shaklas b'shmei ka'amarta. When you said, 'I'm... and pay attention, I'm
going to want another document from him,' maybe I thought the 'him'
meant Joe. I didn't know the 'him' meant me. I thought you
meant you had telling them that now you're going to go to
Joe, get a document from Joe. קא משמע לן, Kamashma lan, דאמר
ליה, d'amar lei, that I can say back to Michael, להכי טרחי
ואמרי להו לקמך, l'hachi tarchi v'amri lehu l'ka-mach, no, that's why I
was telling them in your presence so you should be aware of
that, דמינך הוא דקבעינא, d'minach hu d'kaba'ina, that I want it from
you. Okay, that was all quite fascinating. Really nothing to do with
what we're discussing before. The bridge was this discussion of when I
purchase something from somebody in somebody else's on behalf of somebody else,
do I have to inform the seller of what I'm doing? And
that came from this whole idea of switching the conditions of the
person who gave me money to invest. By the way, of course
the question that you always come up with here, and I really
don't know the answer, is like how could the גמרא Gemara work
through all the details of this and never raise a voice, raise
a voice of objection about sort of like, you know, the trickery
that's going on? You know, so I don't know the answer to
that. Like again, it seems like this was like a standard convention
that you could, you know, do these types of things, but like,
yeah, why is this legal exactly to write it in somebody's name
and it's not a real binding document and I don't know. Alright,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, רב כהנא יהיב זוזי
אכיתנא. Rav Kahana yeiv zuzei a'kitna. Okay now again talking going back
to the idea of sort of like investing money and for whom
you're buying it and when you own it. I mean again these
are all somewhat loosely connected. So רב כהנא Rav Kahana here gave
money for flax. Okay, so רב כהנא Rav Kahana here gave money
to Michael again. Michael's in a lot of business dealings today. and
Michael's a flax trader and he gave him a thousand dollars for
some flax of Michael. וסוף יקר כיתנא. Vesof yakar kitna. And then
the flax market went up and now that flax that he paid
a thousand dollars for is worth twelve hundred dollars. So he didn't
do משיכה, meshicha, right? Well, that's not clear. The גמרא Gemara originally
sounds like he did do, assumes he did.
We'll get to why it assumes that,
I don't know, but that seems to be the initial assumption of
the גמרא, Gemara, that he actually purchased it from Michael, maybe even
did a קנין, kinyan, this is the original assumption of the גמרא,
Gemara, and left it by Michael. Now Michael figured he was going
to, he's going to do a nice favor for רב כהנא. Rav
Kahana. זבני מארוותא דכיתנא. Zavnei marvata dekitna. The owner of the flax
or the original owner according to this sold it. And now he's
got twelve hundred dollars. So basically what happened was he gave רב
כהנא Rav Kahana gave him a thousand, and now he's got twelve
hundred dollars to return to רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. Okay. So אתו
לקמיה דרב, Atu lekamei deRav, so רב כהנא Rav Kahana came to
רב. Rav. Sorry, so is it clear at all why this purchase
was a
purchase of a customer or of the Jew? What? I don't know
if the Jew's going to sell his flax.
Yeah, it's a good question.
So let's take a look at what happens.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רב כהנא Rav Kahana said to רב,
Rav, מאי אעביד, Mai aavid, what should I do? איזיל אשקול זוזי,
Izil eshkol zuzei, so can I go ahead and collect the money,
meaning I paid a thousand and I'm getting twelve hundred? It seems
a little, a little ריבית-like. ribbit Okay. אמר ליה, Amar lei, אי
כזבני, Ei kazavnei, if when Michael sold it, אמרי האי כיתנא דכהנא
הוא, Amri hai kitna deKahana hu, if he said I am selling
רב כהנא'ס Rav Kahana's flax, so then it's sort of like the
issue before. Before we were talking about Michael buying something on behalf
of somebody and informing the seller I am buying this on behalf
of so and so. Here he's selling it. If he's selling it
explicitly in the name of the owner, so because the problem is
that this is going to look like ריבית. ribbit. I gave him
a thousand and I get twelve hundred. But if when Michael sold
it he was announcing I am selling רב כהנא'ס Rav Kahana's flax,
okay, so in that case it's like it's clear. It's my stuff,
he's my agent, it's not ריבית, ribbit, he's just selling something on
my behalf and I'm making a profit. In that case, זיל שקול,
Zil shekol, go take the money. ואי לא, Vei lo, but if
not, לא תשקול, Lo tishkol, you can't take the money because then
now why? Is it because it doesn't look kosher or is it
because in that case maybe he actually, he wasn't, the same way
if he doesn't buy it in my name it's not being bought
for me. If he doesn't sell it in my name it's not
being sold for me. And maybe he was really just a גזלן
gazlan on the flax, okay, and then he stole it and then
he's like giving me back the money or whatever it is, it
makes it a very different transaction maybe. So that's what the גמרא
Gemara asks. כמאן, Keman, who is this going like? כבני מערבא, Kivnei
Maarava, like the בני מערבא Bnei Maarava דאמרי, deamri, מי הודיעו לבעל
חטים שנתן חטים לבעל מעות, mi hodio liva'al chitin shenatan chitin liva'al
ma'ot, who told the seller of the grain that he should sell
the grain to the owner of the money? אטו, Atu, so מי
יהיב רב כהנא ארבעה ושקיל תמניא, mi yahiv Rav Kahana arba'a veshakeil
tamnya, the גמרא Gemara says whatever you say here, whether Michael was
selling it in רב כהנא'ס Rav Kahana's name for these purposes, whether
Michael was selling it in my name or not selling it in
my name. It's not like I gave Michael four dollars and then
he just gave me back eight like it's a straight ריבית ribbit
case. So what happened was I owned the flax. כיתנא ממילא הוא
דיקר מנפשיה. Kitna mimila hu deyakar minefshia. The flax went up in
value. I bought the flax for four, it's now worth eight. So
if he sold it in my name, he's just an agent and
I made a profit. Let's say he didn't sell it in my
name. Let's say when he sold it because he wasn't saying it
was in my name, he was actually effectively stealing my flax and
selling it. Okay, he stole my flax. How much was my flax
worth? Eight dollars. So he pays me eight. Not because of ריבית,
ribbit, because it was my flax that I bought for four and
then when he stole it it was worth eight. Either way, whether
he's selling it on my behalf and I'm making a profit because
he's just being my agent, or whether he sold it and is
selling it on his own behalf, either way it's not like I
didn't own the flax in the middle in the interim, I did.
So he's either just doing it for my behalf or stealing it.
And the same thing would be if I took it to sell
at some point but then waited and then meanwhile the flax price
fluctuated.
All right, so you could have that case, but that wasn't the
case here. So in that case מיגו דגזליה, Migo degazlei, so he's
a thief. Either he's my agent or he's a thief. Either way
I'm entitled to the eight, that's what it was worth. דתנן, Detnan,
מכל גזלן משלם mikal gazlan meshalem כשעת הגזילה. kesha'at hagezeilah. So even
if when I bought it it was worth four, when he stole
it it was worth eight. So what sense does this make? Why
should there be a problem? Either he's my agent in selling it
or he's a גזלן. gazlan. Either way I should be entitled to
the additional price. Yeah, same thing the other way around. Okay, but
maybe that wasn't the scenario. This was an abstract question, it was
a concrete case. Okay, אמרי, Amri, no, התם, Hatam, what happened? I
don't know. But let's see the answer. אמנה הוי. Amana havei. No,
no, no. I didn't actually purchase the flax yet. אמנה הוי Amana
havei means basically I purchased it, I paid Michael the money in
advance. I purchased the flax as a future, okay? So I gave
him four dollars, okay, and basically we assumed that that would be
one bundle of flax, but I never took possession of the flax,
okay? So he owed me, the agreement was that he was going
to sell me a bundle at the four dollar rate that I
paid him for. By the time it came time to actually sell,
give me the flax, right, I bought a future a month from
now, the flax was actually worth eight dollars a bundle. So he
now is going to, if he just gives me eight dollars... He
says, "You know what? Instead of giving you the bundle flax, which
I know I owe you, right, I'll just give you the eight
dollars, that's what it's worth right now." Then we have a little
bit of a problem, right? Because then I gave him four, I
never took possession of anything and he gave me back eight. That
looks like רבית. ribbis. Okay, right? There was never any flax that
I took possession of in the interim. Okay, so ולא משכה רב
כהנא לכתנא V'lo mashcha Rav Kahana l'kitna and Rav Kahana never actually
took possession of the flax. ורב לטעמיה, V'Rav l'ta'amei, Rav is going
according to his reasoning, דאמר רב, d'amar Rav, עושין אמנה בפירות ואין
עושין אמנה בדמים. osin amana b'peiros v'ein osin amana b'damim. You can
prepurchase stuff if you take delivery of the object. So even if
I paid him four now and when he delivered it, it was
worth eight, that's not רבית. ribbis. Okay, because then even though the
thing he gave me was worth eight and I only gave him
four, I mean again, it wasn't a loan, it was a prepurchase
and that, that's okay, that's כשר. kosher. But if in the end
of the day he pays me the value of the thing he
should be delivering and he paid me eight and I gave him
four and I never took possession of the object in the interim,
then that looks too much like רבית ribbis and that's not allowed.
Okay, now, by... so that's why it was problematic, because it was
basically this prepurchase of the flax. But what it doesn't... but apparently
what's not being clear is what's the case that it's okay. So
presumably if Michael had flax, okay, I paid him the four bucks,
then he went ahead and he took possession of a lot of
flax, he had a lot of contracts out there, whatever, right? By
then and then he sold the flax and he got the money
and then he came to me and he just said, "You know
what, if... here's the eight dollars." Right? You invested four, here's your
eight dollars, goodbye. That's not okay because he didn't sell the flax
in my name. At the end of the day, all that happened
was I gave four and I got eight, there was no possession.
But if Michael took possession of all this flax and then he
sold it and said, "Here, I'm selling Rav Kahana's
flax for him" and
then
he got the money, presumably that would have made it כשר. kosher.
That would have somehow made it as if I took possession of
the flax and then he was just selling it for me. Okay.
How does that... how does that work? How does that... that opinion
work? Like, yeah, it's a good question. Like in general these whole
things about like, you know, is it being קונה דבר שלא בא
לעולם? koneh davar she'lo ba l'olam? And exactly, you know, to what
degree is
this real רבית ribbis or just looks like רבית? ribbis?
So as you can imagine, those are like big סוגיות. sugyas. But
the basic point is that as... if he is actually selling flax
in my name and even... and gave me eight even though I
never took possession, that would have made it more כשר. kosher.
Do they not even need an היתר עיסקא? heter iska? I don't
understand how this gets around
a רבית ribbis problem in
this specific context of buying futures. היתר עיסקא heter iska is a
device to use for normal loans.
Like, but I'm saying, meaning you don't... I don't need a היתר
עיסקא. heter iska. Right, because... right. So but let's say I haven't...
so but let's say he didn't sell in your name, then if
we had היתר עיסקא heter iska that'd be okay. Yeah, but it's
hard to imagine how a היתר עיסקא heter iska would work altogether
on a futures purchase. Anyway, but whatever, there's always a way to
make it work. Okay, let's take a look at the משנה. mishnah.
All right. Now we switch gears. So until now we have really
been dealing with variations of the idea of שינוי קונה. shinui koneh.
It... you know, and some of the most... the stuff at the
end wasn't exactly גזלן, gazlan, it was interesting derivations of that. If
a גזלן gazlan is קונה koneh with a שינוי, shinui, what about
if you're a craftsman and you change the object? You go outside
the instructions, to what degree did you take possession of the object?
You weren't intending to steal it but ultimately you transformed somebody's physical
object. And then it would go to even a more extreme application
which is hard to understand exactly the logic of how to connect
the dots, which is you're given money to invest and you invest
it not following the instructions, to what degree is that like a
type of a שינוי קונה shinui koneh and it means that somehow
you've stolen that money and now you take possession of the object
and you owe the guy the original money. Okay, now we switch...
put all that aside and we go to another idea about גזילה,
gezelah, which is the case in the תורה Torah about a very
specific case about swearing falsely that you have a stolen object, and
it's not limited to a stolen object, it could be money that
you were given as a loan, it could be a lost object
that you find, for whatever reason I have something of somebody's in
my possession, whether taken legally or illegally, and the person says, "You
have it" and I say I don't, and I swear falsely and
then I admit, I have to return... this is the פסוק pasuk
at the end of... of פרשת ויקרא, parshat Vayikra, פרק ה׳, perek
heh, I basically have to return the object itself, והשיב את הגזילה
אשר גזל v'heshiv es hagezeilah asher gazal או את העושק אשר עשק
o es ha'oshek asher ashak או את הפקדון אשר הפקד אתו. o
es hapikadon asher hofkad ito. Okay, and then I actually add a
fifth which in rabbinic math is a fourth because if it's worth
four and I add a quarter and I add one then it's
a fifth of the resultant total so it's a quarter of the
base, וחמישיתו יוסף עליו, vachamishiso yosef alav, and I add a fifth
and then it's ואשמו יביא לה׳. v'ashamo yavi l'Hashem. אשם גזילות. Asham
gezelos. Okay, so do we... here we focus not on the אשם
asham but on the idea of the fifth. I should also say
at the beginning that an interesting part about this is the פסוק
pasuk that we've been quoting since the beginning of this פרק perek
to speak about my obligation to return a stolen object is והשיב
את הגזילה אשר גזל, v'heshiv es hagezeilah asher gazal, right, and from
there by the way we learn a lot of things about שינוי,
shinui, אשר גזל כעין שגזל, asher gazal k'ein shegazal, all those things.
Okay, but even though that appears in a פרשה parsha about swearing
falsely, we assume it applies to all גזילות. gezelos. Here we are
going to assume that my obligation of how far do I have
to go to return the object might be a height So here
we're going to assume although the basic obligation of a גזלן Gazlan
is learned also from this פרשה, Parsha, we're going to assume that
this פסוק pasuk that emphasizes a more heightened obligation to fully return
it is only in the case of when I swore falsely. So
let's take a look at this משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so do I
have to go back and pay more? If it's still there and
like the guy’s, you know, I sold it to Joe over there
and Joe is just like, no, you know, I know this is
Rabbi Bunim's sentimental whatever it is, I'm going to demand twenty percent
more. Okay, no, no, no, if it's not in your possession you
don't have to.
The question is not the physical object, the question is just reimbursing
me, either giving me back the physical object if you still have
it or reimbursing me if you don't. But still how far do
you have to go to make sure that I get paid? Let's
take a look.
I don't have to go at all. No, no, correct. הגוזל את
חברו שוה פרוטה, Hagozel et chaveiro shaveh peruta, if you steal a
שוה פרוטה, shaveh peruta, something worth a פרוטה, peruta, which is you
know less than a cent probably at least in today's value, in
today's market value, ונשבע לו, venishba lo, and you've sworn falsely that
you don't have
it, then how far do you have to go to return it?
יוליכנו אחריו למדי. Yolichenu acharaiv leMadai. You have to go all the
way to מדי. Madai. Where’s מדי, Madai, Charlie? No, that’s Persia, Media.
Okay, right, you have to go all the way to Persia to
return it. Presumably even if this was before they had post, you
know, the postal service, meaning presumably even if it’s only a dollar,
you have to spend a thousand dollars to get it back to
the guy. Meaning יוליכנו אחריו למדי. Yolichenu acharaiv leMadai. Yeah, if he's
in מדי, Madai, right.
Okay, can I wait for him to come back?
So you could wait, but you would not have been getting your
כפרה kapara yet, you know, and if I'm never coming back you’ll
never get your כפרה. kapara. Okay, so לא יתן לא לבנו ולא
לשלוחו. lo yiten lo livno velo lishlucho. You cannot give to your
son or maybe even the son
of the person who you owe
the money for or his messenger.
אבל נותן לשליח
בית דין.
Aval
noten leshaliach Beit Din.
You can give it to a messenger of the court. Wait, לשלוחו
lishlucho means your messenger or mine or my messenger? So we'll see
in the גמרא. Gemara. His messenger, why can't you give it to
his messenger? Right, so we will see that in the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, right, you would think that if I sent a messenger you
could, fine. But certainly anyway the פשט pshat is that look at
רש״י. Rashi. לא יתן לא לבנו, Lo yiten lo livno, so Michael
rightly thinks that presumably we mean I can't give to my son,
presumably I can give to Michael's son if he's
the one I stole it from or his messenger.
רש״י Rashi says, לא יתן לא לבנו, lo yiten lo livno, של
נגזל. shel nigzal.
לא ניחא לנגזל. Lo nicha lenigzal.
Now, it doesn't mean you can't. I can if it gets to
Michael געזונטערהייט, gezunterheit, but the point of I can’t means I can’t
assume that I fully sort of you know got off of any
responsibility שאם יאנסוהו חייב להחזיר. she’im ye’ansuhu chayav lehachazir. דלא הוי השבה
עד דמטי לידיה. Delo havei hashava ad demati leidei. Okay, that yes,
I can give it to my messenger, I can even give it
to Michael's messenger, but if the money gets lost on the journey
before it gets to Michael's hands, then I still have not satisfied
my obligation. Now again, that’s a pretty big shocker because you would
think like if I give it to the messenger, the messenger could
take possession for Michael. If Michael is sending the messenger, isn't he
implicitly telling me that once I give it to the messenger I'm
off the hook? So all of this the גמרא Gemara will ask.
Okay, but the one person I can give it to is a
שליח בית דין. shaliach Beit Din. There I can, I assume once
I've given it to the שליח בית דין, shaliach Beit Din, you
know, I'm no longer responsible for any loss and they'll make sure
it gets to Michael and if not, well, if not, then why
will I be off the hook? It's not exactly clear. Will they
reimburse Michael or are we just saying that I've done my duty,
you know, and Michael, we'll both be out the money? We’re going
to talk about that. The fact that it goes to the שליח
בית דין. shaliach Beit Din. יהו? Yehu? הנגזל, Hanigzal, yeah, apparently. Right,
so he's in מדי, Madai, you know, it doesn't get to Michael.
Right. So רש״י Rashi thinks that the whole idea of a שליח
בית דין, shaliach Beit Din, if you look at רש״י, Rashi, תקנה
הוא, takana hu, דרבנן, de-rabbanan, מפני תקנת השבים. mipnei takanat hashavim. That
that was in order to make it easier for me because now
that you've told me I have to run off to Michael all
the way, you know, to China,
so whoever, you know, I'm just
not going to bother trying to return it. So חז״ל Chazal tried
to make it easier, you
know, give it to a שליח בית דין shaliach Beit Din then
you'll be יוצא.
yotzei. תוספות Tosafot sort of questions to what degree this is a
תקנה takana or is it the same תקנה takana as a different
type of a תקנה takana that we’re going to encounter later in
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, but anyway let's keep on reading the משנה.
Mishnah. We’ll unpack all this when we get to the גמרא. Gemara.
ואם מת יחזיר ליורשיו. Ve'im met yachazir leyorshav. Now if the נגזל
nigzal died, don't think like, you know, because this is about the
purpose about this is that since this is all tied into the
פסוקים pesukim to the idea of bringing a קרבן, korban, the question
here is now not just a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot obligation but
there's almost like a כפרה kapara obligation. to their heirs because it's
the it's money owed to the estate. But here the חידוש chiddush
is that even when I return it to the heirs and not
to the person I wronged, right, from a כפרה kaparah perspective, that
still somehow satisfies and then I return it to the estate and
I can bring my קרבן korban and still get כפרה. kaparah. נתן
לו את הקרן, Natan lo et hakeren, now let's say I returned
to the person I stole it from the principal, ולא נתן לו
את החומש, velo natan lo et hachomesh, I didn't return the fifth
because I swore falsely and I owed a fifth. Okay, מחל לו
על הקרן, machal lo al hakeren, let's say the person who I
stole it from said, you know what, forget the principal, ולא מחל
לו החומש, velo machal lo hachomesh, but I'm not going to be
מוחל mochel the חומש, chomesh, which is a little funny obviously that's
a lot less money, but maybe he was making a point, right,
you know, it's like I really don't, you know, forget about the
money, but I want you to still pay me that חומש chomesh
because that shows like you know that you're accepting guilt and fault
and your responsibility or whatever. Do you usually explicitly do it or
like if he said, alright I'm מוחל, mochel, does it assume that
you're מוחל mochel the חומש? chomesh? Presumably you're מוחל mochel both. But
this is just the scenario because it wants to focus us on
the halakhic status of the חומש. chomesh. Okay, so ולא מחל לו
החומש, velo machal lo hachomesh, מחל לו על זה ועל זה חוץ
מפחות משוה פרוטה שבקרן, machal lo al zeh ve'al zeh chutz mifachos
m'shaveh prutah she'bakeren, or he was מוחל mochel both with the exception
of one פרוטה, prutah, okay, that
he wasn't מוחל mochel on, excuse me, less than one פרוטה, prutah,
did I skip a line?
No. מחל לו על הקרן ולא מחל לו החומש, machal lo al
hakeren velo machal lo hachomesh, מחל לו על זה ועל זה חוץ
מפחות משוה פרוטה machal lo al zeh ve'al zeh chutz mifachos m'shaveh
prutah less than one פרוטה prutah of the קרן, keren, in that
case, אינו צריך ללכת אחריו. eino tzarich lalechet acharav. I still owe
him the money, but I don't have to go all the way
after him to find him. Okay, I only have to go after
him to China to return the principal, והשיב את הגזלה אשר גזל,
v'heshiv et hagezeilah asher gazal, right? So therefore if what I if
there's less than anything that's considered value, less than a פרוטה, prutah,
or what I owe him is a חומש, chomesh, but that's a
fine, that's added on top, that's not the thing that I stole,
that's just now additional money that I owe him, then yes, I
still owe him that money, but I don't have to run after
him to the end of the earth to get it back from
him. When you come I'll pay you, okay, yes, I owe you
the money, I'm not but I'm not going to crazy lengths to
get it back to you. Now, אינו צריך, eino tzarich, נתן לו
את החומש ולא נתן לו את הקרן, natan lo et hachomesh velo
natan lo et hakeren, how if it's the reverse? I paid him
the fifth and not the principal. מחל לו על החומש ולא מחל
לו הקרן, machal lo al hachomesh velo machal lo hakeren, or he
was מוחל mochel the fifth but he wasn't מוחל mochel the principal.
מחל לו על זה ועל זה, machal lo al zeh ve'al zeh,
he was מוחל mochel the whole thing, חוץ משוה פרוטה בקרן chutz
mishaveh prutah bakeren except for one penny's worth of the principal, צריך
ללכת אחריו. tzarich lalechet acharav. I have to go after him, okay?
So it's not the amount, dollar amount, it's the principal. As long
as there's a פרוטה's prutah worth of the principal, that's the obligation.
Other money I owe him is not to that extent. נתן לו
את הקרן ונשבע לו על החומש. natan lo et hakeren venishba lo
al hachomesh. Now, let's say I paid Michael back, it was $100
and I paid Michael back the $100, I swore falsely about it
and now the חומש chomesh is 25, okay? I paid Michael back
the $100 and Michael said thank you very much, but what about
the other 25 that you owe me? And I say, no no
no, I already paid that back. He says, take a שבועה. shvua.
So I take a שבועה. shvua. So now it's like history repeats
itself, I'm swearing falsely not on the principal, but on the חומש.
chomesh. Okay, so now I'm essentially stealing the חומש chomesh and swearing
falsely on it. הרי זה מוסיף חומש על חומש. harei zeh mosif
chomesh al chomesh. So now I have to pay a fifth on
the fifth, okay? Which would be what, what would that be? Six
and a quarter or something. Anyway, okay, על חומש, al chomesh, עד
שימעט הקרן משוה פרוטה. ad sheyismaat hakeren mishaveh prutah. And now I
owe Michael, so then I finally, okay fine, now I owe an
extra six and a quarter for the 25. Then I admit to
it. Fine, you're right, I was lying, here's the 25. And he
goes great, where's the six and a quarter? What six and a
quarter? I paid that already. So you're again and again until the
principal gets less than a פרוטה. prutah. עד שימעט הקרן משוה פרוטה.
ad sheyismaat hakeren mishaveh prutah. Now the interesting thing is if the
principal's a פרוטה, prutah, then I owe him a fifth of a
פרוטה prutah or a quarter of a פרוטה. prutah. I don't know
exactly how I pay him that, okay? But this you still have
to keep on the idea that you could be נשבע nishba and
have all of these consequences and bring a קרבן korban and the
whole thing, it doesn't have to have started with something I stole,
it could even just start with this additional fine and as long
as there's a פרוטה's prutah worth, all these consequences apply. וכן בפקדון.
v'chein b'pikadon. Every time? Every time for every oath he brings an
אשם, asham, yeah. It's a little bit and bringing a whole big
קרבן? korban? Exactly, because of this fantastic, this real honest desire to
do, I don't know, it's interesting. וכן בפקדון. v'chein b'pikadon. Now the
same way this is true if I stole the money and swore
falsely, it really doesn't matter how I got the money initially, even
though I
got the money legitimately
initially, like it was a it was something that was kept
for safekeeping, שנאמר, shene'emar, או פקדון או תשומת יד או גזל,
o pikadon o
tishumas
yad o gazel, okay, or תשומת יד tishumas yad which is basically
some type
of impropriety, רש"י Rashi actually says, actually רש"י Rashi says it's not
an impropriety, רש"י Rashi says it's actually a loan that I'm denying
or something I stole, או עשק את עמיתו o ashak et amiso
or that's the impropriety, I somehow you know withheld money from you
that you were owing him, או מצא אבידה וכחש בה o matza
aveidah v'kichash bah or a lost object that I found and I
denied I found it, anyway whether I got the money legitimately or
not, now I'm denying it, ונשבע על שקר, v'nishba al shaker, I
swore falsely, הרי זה משלם קרן וחומש ואשם, harei zeh m'shalem keren
v'chomesh v'asham, pay the principal, the fifth, and the אשם. asham. Okay,
so anyway the bottom line is... to pay the principal, the fifth
and the אשם. Asham. Okay, so it’s anyway the bottom line is
though is that it’s clear that by a normal גזילה Gezeilah for
whatever reason I have to give you back the money but maybe
I don’t have to expend any effort and expense because the basic
principle from the beginning of this פרק Perek is how nice, how
easy we go on the גזלן, Gazlan, right? Only if I swear
falsely, then I have to like run after you and if I
don’t run after you, like you know I can’t say I’ve done
my due diligence. I’m ultimately have not fulfilled my obligation, you know,
and I won’t be able to bring my קרבן, Korban, I won’t
be able to get כפרה Kapparah and so on. Yes, Charlie. You
mentioned postal service both the Persian Empire and the Roman Empire had
postal service. Oh, excellent. So it makes it that much easier to
get it to מדי. Maddai. But I’m not פטור Patur if it
doesn’t get to him. That’s the הלכה Halakha of the משנה. Mishna.
I’m not sure that you could send anything
from the Roman Empire where the משנה Mishna would’ve been written to
the Persian. Ah, that’s a good question.
Got it, got it. So considering if there is a פרט וכלל,
Prat u'klal, או מצא אבדה, O matza aveda, and then it says
או אשר יחטא אדם
לחטו.
O asher yecheta
adam lachato.
That’s interesting. Do we do a פרט כלל פרט? Prat klal prat?
I’m not sure, I don’t remember. Okay, I haven’t gotten to it
yet.
I don’t know, it’s a good question. Okay, yeah.
So if you didn’t swear falsely and the guy isn’t in מדי,
Maddai, what’s your obligation to get it to him? Yeah, so the
גמרא, Gemara, that’s not so clear.
I mean but to some degree that’s going to be explored right
here at the beginning of the גמרא. Gemara. So let’s take a
look at the גמרא.
Gemara. Okay, it is very funny, right? How is it that we’ve
been talking all this time and we only talk
about
the extent of the obligation when we get to this שבועה? Shevuah?
What about all the normal cases? So let’s look at the גמרא.
Gemara. נשבע לו אין, Nishba lo in, so here is the first
thing the גמרא Gemara asks. This is your obligation when you swear
falsely. לא נשבע לו לא, Lo nishba lo lo, not if you
don’t swear falsely. מני, Mani, who is this going like? לא רבי
טרפון ולא רבי עקיבא, Lo Rabbi Tarfon v'lo Rabbi Akiva, neither רבי
טרפון Rabbi Tarfon nor רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. דתניא, De-tanya, we learn
in a ברייתא. Baraita. גזל לאחד מחמשה ואינו יודע איזה מהם גזל,
Gezal le-echad me-chamisha ve-eino yodeia eizeh me-hem gazal, או איזה מהם. O
eizeh me-hem. וכל אחד אומר אותי גזל. Ve-chol echad omer oti gazal.
So basically I stole from one of you guys. I’m not going
to tell you which one, one of you guys left ten dollars
on this table beforehand, last year. I stole it from you, but
I don’t know which one of you I stole from, whose money
it was. Everybody here claims that it was you who I stole
from. What’s my responsibility? Okay? מניח גזילה ביניהם ומסתלק דברי רבי טרפון.
Mani'ach gezeilah beineichem u-mistalek, divrei Rabbi Tarfon. רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says
I say here, here’s the ten dollars, I put it on the
table, you guys fight it out. I walk out of the room.
That satisfies my obligation. Which is pretty funny. Even דיני שמים? Dinei
shamayim? Right, well we’re going to see about the even דיני שמים
Dinei shamayim in a minute, in a little bit, which is pretty
funny because you would think that if I stole, I’m not פטור
Patur until I make sure that the person got the money back.
Okay, so that’s רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. רבי עקיבא אומר לא זו
הדרך מוציאה מידי עבירה. Rabbi Akiva omer lo zu ha-derekh motzi'ah mi-yedei
aveira. This is not the way that I get out of sinning.
Now is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva talking about דיני שמים Dinei shamayim
or דיני אדם? Dinei adam? It sounds a little bit like he’s
talking about דיני שמים. Dinei shamayim. Anyway, עד שישלם גזילה לכל אחד
ואחד. Ad she-ye-shalem gezeilah le-chol echad ve-echad. I have to pay every
one of you. Now by the way, before we get to unpacking
that, תוספות Tosafot asks a really good question. תוספות Tosafot says how
does this sit in with the general issue we have of ברי
ושמא? Bari ve-shema? Michael comes to me and says Dov, you owe
me ten dollars. And I say I don’t know. So there’s a
debate whether we say this ברי Bari win and I have to
give him ten dollars, or does this ברי Bari not win and
I don’t. So how is this any different? Okay, here all of
you are saying hey, that’s my money you’re... and I say I
don’t know. So if we normally say ברי ושמא, Bari shema, ברי
עדיף, Bari adif, if we normally say I have to give to
the guy who says, why do I have to pay all of
you? So תוספות Tosafot says an obvious answer. Because here, four out
of the five of you are lying. So when do we say
that a ברי Bari is עדיף? Adif? Is you say yes, I
say I don’t know, there’s nothing that contradicts your statement. Here, the
other four claims contradict your statement, okay? So that’s why even if
we normally say ברי עדיף, Bari adif, here I wouldn’t have to
pay. And תוספות Tosafot says also the reverse. The reverse is, according
to the one that says normally, Michael says hey, you owe me
ten dollars and I say I don’t know, that I don’t have
to pay. Here it could make sense that you could say I
would have to pay. Why would here I definitely have to pay
if and when normally Michael comes to me and says Dov, you
owe me ten dollars and I say I don’t know, I don’t
have to pay, why here would רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva say that
I definitely have to pay? Because here I admit I owe one
of you ten dollars, I just don’t know which one. Okay? So
this case is sort of different on both ends.
It starts with one guy is definitely admitting, okay? He’s not saying
he doesn’t know.
And everybody else is making a definite claim but contradicted by everybody
else’s claim. But what do you do with the פסוק Pasuk of
אשר הוא לו יתנו לו יום אשמו? Asher hu lo yitnu lo
yom ashamo? מניח גזילה ביניהם. Mani'ach gezeilah beineichem. That פסוק Pasuk of
אשר הוא לו, Asher hu lo, which is the emphasis of the
משנה, Mishna, יוליך ואחריו למדי, Yoilich v'achrei-av le-Maddai, is by case of
שבועה. Shevuah. Okay, but let’s take a look at this גמרא. Gemara.
גמרא Gemara says who is our משנה Mishna going like? Okay, neither
רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon nor רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Okay, why? Mani,
אי רבי טרפון, אף על גב דאשתבע אמר מניח גזילה ביניהם ומסתלק.
i-Rabbi Tarfon af al gav de-ishtaba amar mani'ach gezeilah beineichem u-mistalek. So
we assume that the case is, we assume that the case of
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon is the case
that, one minute, אי רבי טרפון i-Rabbi Tarfon, אף על גב דאשתבע
אמר מניח גזילה ביניהם ומסתלק. af al gav de-ishtaba amar mani'ach gezeilah
beineichem u-mistalek. So we assume that we’re not making a distinction in
the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon debate initially
whether you made a שבועה Shevuah or didn’t make a שבועה. Shevuah.
So if it doesn’t make a difference whether you did or you
didn’t, then our משנה Mishna doesn’t work out. Because רבי טרפון Rabbi
Tarfon seems to say in all cases just leave the גזילה Gezeilah
and walk away. אף על גב דלא אישתבע אמר ישלם גזלה לכל
אחד ואחד. Af al gav delo ishtaba amar yishalem gezeila l'chol echad
v'echad. Okay, so that's assuming that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי
טרפון Rabbi Tarfon don't distinguish between making a שבועה shvoo and not.
Okay, so then how would it work out? So the גמרא Gemara
says, well let's say it makes a difference. לעולם רבי עקיבא היא.
Le'olam Rabbi Akiva hi. Let, I'll tell you that our משנה mishna
is רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. וכי קאמר רבי עקיבא עד שישלם גזילה
לכל אחד ואחד היכא דאישתבע הוא דקאמר. V'chi ka'amar Rabbi Akiva ad
sheyishalem gezeila l'chol echad v'echad heicha de'ishtaba hu d'ka'amar. Now רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva isn't talking about all cases. The debate of רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon is you made a שבועה.
shvoo. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says if you made a שבועה,
shvoo, you gotta make sure the guy gets the money back. That's
why you have to pay every single one and that's why in
our משנה mishna you have to run after him to מדי. Madai.
If you didn't make a שבועה, shvoo, maybe רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
would say you let them fight it out and you don't run
after him to מדי. Madai. So our משנה mishna that expresses, that's
the obvious thing, is to link our משנה mishna that expresses running
after the guy to China with רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who clearly
expresses a heightened responsibility to make sure that the thing gets returned.
Okay, so we're saying if our משנה's mishna going to limit it
to שבועה, shvoo, we'll say that רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva limited to
a case of שבועה. shvoo. And when you say if not שבועה,
shvoo, but let's take a look. Okay, וגרסינן הכי אף על גב
דלא אישתבע אמר ישלם גזלה לכל אחד ואחד אלא לעולם רבי עקיבא
וכי קאמר רבי עקיבא עד שישלם גזלה לכל אחד ואחד היכא דאשתבע
הוא דקאמר מאי טעמא דאמר קרא.
V'garsinan hachi af al gav delo ishtaba amar yishalem gezeila l'chol echad
v'echad ella le'olam Rabbi Akiva v'chi ka'amar Rabbi Akiva ad sheyishalem gezeila
l'chol echad v'echad heicha
de'ishtaba hu
d'ka'amar mai ta'ama d'amar kra. Here's the פסוק pasuk as Michael was
quoting: לאשר הוא לו יתננו ביום אשמתו. L'asher hu lo yitnenu b'yom
ashmato. When he was, when there's an אשמה, ashama, when there's a
day of real guilt as a swore falsely you have to really
make sure everybody gets it back. So either pay five people or
run after him to מדי, Madai, that's your heightened obligation. And רבי
טרפון Rabbi Tarfon would be saying אף על גב דאישתבע. af al
gav de'ishtaba. So now what? רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon doesn't make any
sense. You took a שבועה shvoo and you could just put the
money and walk away? Yes, אבל רבנן תקנתא. aval rabanan takanta. The
Rabbis made a תקנה. takanta. They said to you they were going
to make it easy for you to pay up. Okay, even if
you took a שבועה. shvoo. דתני רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק אומר. D'tani
Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Tzadok omer. Rabbi Elazar ben Rabbi Tzadok says commenting
on our משנה mishna that you have to run after him to
מדי: Madai: תקנה גדולה התקינו. Takana gedola hitkinu. It's not true that
you don't always have to run after him to China. They made
a תקנה. takana. שאם היתה הוצאה יתירה על הקרן. She'im hayta hotza'ah
yeteirah al hakeren. If the travel expenses exceeded the principal that you
were returning, משלם קרן וחומש לבית דין. meshalem keren v'chomesh l'veit din.
You just pay the court. ומביא אשמו ומתכפר לו. Umeivi ashamo umitkaper
lo. And you go bring an אשם asham and you're done with
it. Now רש"י Rashi says this תקנה takana is the same of
the משנה mishna of שליח בית דין. shaliach beit din. תוספות Tosafot
says it's not. תוספות Tosafot says the שליח בית דין shaliach beit
din is is that the money still has to get to the
guy, it's just by giving it to a שליח shaliach of the
court you're free from any responsibility if it gets lost or anything
happens. Here, the money is left at the בית דין beit din
and the guy has to come pick it up at the בית
דין. beit din. Nobody is running after to get the money to
the guy. Okay, but either way that's not exactly our concern right
now. The basic point is that רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק Rabbi Elazar
b'Rabbi Tzadok is saying that in many cases where there's a high
expense you don't have to run after the guy, just give it
to the בית דין. beit din. No expense, the guy stole a
million dollars from you and it cost five thousand dollars to get
there. Right, high expense, relatively high expense, expense is greater than the
cost. So therefore in the case of when
I stole it to five people, right, making sure the person would
get
it back is going to exceed the principal by four times because
I'm going to have to pay everybody. So therefore similar to the
idea of not running after him to China and leaving it with
a בית דין, beit din, I leave it among them. Now does
leaving it among them put it on the table or does it
mean I give the money to בית דין beit din and let
them fight it out in בית דין? beit din? Okay, according to
this it makes more sense to say the latter. Okay, so here
basically the point is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva doesn't hold of any
תקנה. takana. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says run after him to China,
give to five people, if you swore falsely do whatever it needs
to make sure the guy gets the money back. And if you
didn't, we don't know if you didn't swear falsely. And רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon says even in principle maybe I agree, you don't have
to spend more than the principal, in principle, different principle. You don't
have to spend more than the amount that you stole. So don't
run after him to China, give it to בית דין. beit din.
Don't pay five people, give it to בית דין, beit din, let
them fight it out. Okay, so that's one way of explaining it.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ורבי עקיבא. V'Rabbi Akiva.
And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say back no: כהאי רבנן תקנתא.
K'hai rabanan takanta. Look, it might make sense to say the Rabbis
made a תקנה takana היכא דידע למאן גזליה. heicha deyada l'man gazlei.
If I know that I stole it from Michael, so I'm not
going to go fly to China, I'll put it in the בית
דין beit din but eventually I know Michael's going to get his
money back when he picks it up from the בית דין beit
din or they send it to him. דקמהדר ממונא למריה. D'kamahadar mamona
l'mareih. The money's going to get back to Michael eventually. There maybe
I'll concede, don't fly to China, put the money with the בית
דין. beit din. But גזל אחד מחמשה gezel echad mechamesha דלא ידע
למאן גזל, d'lo yada l'man gazal, but when I stole from five
and I don't know from whom and I'm going to give it
to a בית דין beit din and I don't know the person's
ever going to get his money back, דלא אהדורי ממונא למריה, d'lo
ahadurei mamona l'mareih, the person won't necessarily ever get his money back,
לא עבדי רבנן תקנתא. lo avdi rabanan takanta. I'm sorry, I cannot
accept that a תקנה takana would apply in such a case. Okay,
so even if in principle I'm willing to assume a תקנה, takana,
certainly not in the case of five. So one way of explaining
it is that we made a שבועה. shvoo. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
is, that's the easiest way, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who expresses an
idea. ensure the money gets back is the one who says in
the משנה mishna you got to fly to China, רבי טרפון Rabbi
Tarfon is not so concerned even in the case of a שבועה,
shevua, he says there are ways we deal with it that you
don't have to go to such crazy extent even if the guy,
even if there are five people and the guy might not get
his money back in the end. That's one way of explaining it.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this: where were we? Okay.
מתיב רב הונא בר יהודה. Masiv Rav Huna bar Yehuda. רב הונא
בר יהודה Rav Huna bar Yehuda asks. אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
לא נחלקו רבי טרפון ורבי עקיבא על שלקח אחד מחמשה בני אדם
ואין יודע ממי לקח שמניח דמי מקח ביניהם ומסתלק. Amar Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar lo nechlaku Rabbi Tarfon veRabbi Akiva al shelakach echad mechamesh
bnei adam vehein yodea mimi lakach shemianich dmei mekach beineihem veyistalek. They
don't debate if it wasn't a case of גזל. gezel. Let's say
it was a case of honest mistake. I purchased one an object
from one of the five of you. You were five merchants in
a market, and I bought something from one of you and I
don't remember which one and all of you are claiming I you're
the one I bought it from. So in that case we all
agree that I put the money down and I let you guys
fight it out. Okay, cause I didn't do anything wrong, I wasn't
a גזלן. gazlan. על מה נחלקו, Al ma nechlaku, when did we
debate? שגזל אחד מחמשה בני אדם ואין יודע ממי גזל. Shegazal echad
michamesh bnei adam veein yodea mimi gazal. רבי טרפון אומר מניח דמי
גזילה ביניהם ומסתלק. Rabbi Tarfon omer meniach dmei gezeila beineihem veyistalek. רבי
עקיבא אומר אין לו תקנה שישלם לכל אחד ואחד. Rabbi Akiva omer
ein lo takkanah sheyishalem lechol echad veechad. When I did something wrong
and I was a גזלן, gazlan, that's when רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says I have to pay every one of you. Now he says
like this: one minute. אי סלקא דעתך דמשתבע, I salka daatach d'mishtaba,
if you're saying the only time רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says I
pay each one of you is when I took an oath, so
if it's a case that I took an oath, it shouldn't matter
how I got to how I owed you the money to begin
with, right? Because the so מה לי לקח מה לי גזל? mah
li lakach mah li gazal? Whether you whether initially you were גזלן
gazlan or not, at the end of the day, what creates the
heavy obligation is that you swore falsely. That's the case of our
משנה. mishna. So it doesn't matter if it started legitimate. In that
oath, you became a גזלן gazlan and you swore falsely. That should
create the heavy obligation. ועוד, Veod, מתיב רבא. masiv Rava. רבא Rava
asks. מעשה בחסיד אחד. Maaseh bechasid echad. There was a story with
a חסיד chasid שלקח משני בני אדם shelakach mishnei bnei adam ולא
יודע ממי לקח. veLo yodea mimi lakach. He didn't know which one,
just like this case. ובא לפני רבי טרפון. u'va lifnei Rabbi Tarfon.
He came to רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. אמר לו. Amar lo. רבי
טרפון Rabbi Tarfon said, הניח דמי מקח ביניהם ומסתלק. Heniach dmei mekach
beineihem veyistalek. Yeah, just put the money let them fight it out.
בא לפני רבי עקיבא. Ba lifnei Rabbi Akiva. He came to רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. אמר לו, Amar lo, אין לך תקנה שישלם לכל
אחד ואחד. ein lecha takkanah sheyeshalem lechol echad veechad. You have to
pay each one. This presumably argues on the previous point and says
that רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva idea of paying everyone is even if
what you did was legitimate, even if you were just a purchaser,
still you owe somebody money, you're not off the hook until that
person is paid. Fine. But again we have our question. If we're
talking about a שבועת שקר, shvuat shaker, okay, ואי סלקא דעתך דמשתבע,
ve'ei salka daatach demishtaba, that the only case רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
would say it is not only you did your thing but then
you took an oath about it, חסיד מי משתבע בשקרא? chasid mi
mishtaba beshikra? Since when does a righteous person coming and swearing falsely?
A righteous person cannot remember who he owes the money to, but
that he swore falsely? וכי תימא דמשתבע והדר הוה חסיד? V'chi teima
d'mishtaba vehadar hava chasid? Maybe he swore falsely and now he's become
a חסיד chasid and he wants to do the right thing? That's
the case. Good good thing for אלול, Elul, you know, you could
start by being a גזלן gazlan and a משתבע שקר mishtaba shaker
and then be a חסיד. chasid. והא כל היכא דאמרינן, Veha kol
heicha d'amrina, מעשה בחסיד אחד, maaseh bechasid echad, we know whenever we
say a story with a חסיד, chasid, או רבי יהודה בן בבא
או רבי יהודה בר אלעאי. o Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava o Rabbi
Yehuda bar Ilai. Either talking about רבי יהודה בן בבא Rabbi Yehuda
ben Bava or רבי יהודה בר אלעאי, Rabbi Yehuda bar Ilai, one
of these two great תנאים. Tannaim. Okay, רבי יהודה בן בבא, Rabbi
Yehuda ben Bava, רבי יהודה בר אלעאי, Rabbi Yehuda bar Ilai, חסידים
מעיקרא הוו. chasidim meikara havu. They weren't people that started their career
by swearing falsely. They were always righteous people. Okay. So you see
that we cannot limit the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and
רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon to a case of swearing falsely. So what
we'll do is we'll pick up tomorrow now that we know the
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon are talking about
even without swearing. We're going to now try to now that we
know that, now we're going to match them up to the משנה
mishna knowing that we can't since the משנה mishna says you only
have this crazy obligation when you swear falsely, okay, and רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon are talking about when you
didn't swear falsely, then now we're going to try to figure out
who the משנה mishna is going like and we'll
pick
up
with
that
tomorrow.